Guide to the David Hull Papers, 1967-2004 ASP.2005.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
David Hull Papers
1916-2008
1954-2005
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hull, David L.
ASP.2005.01
32.5 Linear Feet (62 document cases and 7 letter/legal boxes with covers)
This material documents the philosophical activity of David L. Hull between the years 1965-2003. This time span encompasses the whole of his professional career and extends into his retirement. The material consists of letters, manuscripts, surveys, background materials for the research surveys, overheads for talks, data sheets, and other texts generated by his professional career. His works address philosophical problems in and historical explication of many areas of biology including classification, taxonomy, theoretical systematics, evolutionary theory, historical biology, and ecology.
Acquisition Information
The original donation of scholarly material was a gift directly from the creator, David L. Hull, in August of 2004. There was a second donation of scrapbooks documenting David Hull's social and professional life which was donated by the executor of his estate after Hull's death.
Previous Citation
David L. Hull Papers, 1965-2004, ASP.2005.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
Letters of recommendation concerning living individuals have been restricted for 25 years from the date of donation. These materials will not be available until 2030. Series III, Photograph Scrapbooks and Miscellaneous Loose Photographs will be restricted until 2044.
Biography
The American Historian and Philosopher of Science, David Lee Hull, was born in Burnside, Illinois, on June 15, 1935 and lived in Chicago, Illinois, until his death on August 11, 2010. He was educated at Wesleyan University where he received a B.A. degree in 1960. He then attended Indiana University at Bloomington where he received the Ph.D. degree in 1964. He taught at the University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, from 1964 to 1984, progressing from assistant to full professor and then being appointed Distinguished Professor of Philosophy. In 1985 he was appointed a professor at Northwestern University and this appointment was followed by appointment to the Dressler Professorship in 1989. Hull remained on the Northwestern faculty until his retirement in 2000.
Hull's work encompassed both history and philosophy of biology and centered on philosophical and historical considerations in theoretical taxonomy, systematics, evolutionary biology and genetics. He contributed significantly to many areas of philosophy of biology on topics such as reductionism, philosophies of systematics, and evolutionary theory. Hull has authored many significant articles and books; among them are What Philosophy of Biology is Not (J. Historical Biology 69), Contemporary Systematic Philosophies (Ann. Rev. of Ecology & Systematics 71), and Reduction in genetics – philosophy or biology? (Philos. Sci. 73).
Scope and Content Notes
The first and largest series of materials from the first donation consists of professional correspondence between David Hull and other philosophers of science as well as academics in related fields. These correspondents were in disciplines such as evolutionary biology whose work was of interest to Hull. The remaining series deal with manuscripts written by Hull.
The second donation consists of scrapbooks documenting Hull's personal and professional life. These scrap books contain material from previous generations of Hull's family as well as photos of his friends and philosophical colleagues.
Arrangement
The records are organized into three series.
Series I. Correspondence, 1960-2004
Series II. Manuscripts and Working Papers
Series III. Photograph Scrapbooks and Miscellaneous Loose Photographs, 1916-2008
Biology -- Philosophy; Evolution (Biology) -- Philosophy; Natural selection -- Philosophy; Natural selection; Knowledge, Theory of; Science -- Methodology; Science -- Philosophy; Hull, David L.; Beardsley, Monroe C.; Ayala, Francisco
- Correspondence, 1960-2004; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  The correspondence covers the period from 1965-2004 and contains the professional scientific and philosophical correspondence of D.L. Hull during the span of his career from his first appointment as professor to the year 2004. It contains letters to and from Hull and also manuscripts or parts of manuscripts that were sent out by Hull for critical response or were sent to him for the same purpose.
  There are two major forms of organization used by Hull. Some authors are to be found only in their own folders, designated by their last name. Others are to be found in folders arranged by letter of the alphabet and then chronologically by range of years. Thus an author whose last name began with A might be found in several folders across a span of time, (e.g. A – 1965-1970, A – 1975-1980, A – 1995-2000 etc.) A correspondent who has one or more folders dedicated solely to their correspondence may then have letters spanning decades in the same folder. It is important to note that some authors may appear in both forms: they may have a folder dedicated to their correspondence but may appear in the more general alphabetical listing in several year ranges. Further, inclusion in the general alphabetic/chronological listing is not indicative of a minor correspondence. Some authors listed only in the alphabetic/chronological listings have fairly extensive correspondence. This correspondence may be limited in time, or restricted by topic, but was not therefor considered by Hull as unimportant. Hence researchers should consult both series of letters when gathering material for research.
  Please note that any folder that contains a manuscript in addition to correspondence will be marked with an asterisk (*).
  - Correspondence "A" and Abrams - Ayala, 1967-2000; 1.
    - "A" Correspondence, 1967-2000 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Abrams (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Abrams (2) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Alder (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Amundson (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ashlock (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Asquith (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Atran (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Aungey (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ayala (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence "B" and Beardsley-Burian, 1966-2003
    - "B" Correspondence, 1966-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3-9)
    - "B" Correspondence, 1984-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1-10)
    - "B" Correspondence, 1995-2003 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - Beardsley-Philosophy of Biological Sciences, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Beatty (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Becker (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Bock (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Bowler (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Brandon (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Brito da Cunha (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Brooks (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Brundin/Croizal (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Buck (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Buller (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Burian (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence "C" and Callebaut-Cronin, 1965-2002
    - "C" Correspondence, 1965-1979 (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
    - "C" Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "C" Correspondence, 1983-1994 (Box 8, Folder 2-7)
    - "C" Correspondence, 1995-2002 (Box 9, Folder 1-7)
    - Callebaut (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Camardi (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Cambell (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Caplan (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Carey (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Colless (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
    - Colless (2) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Collier (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
    - Cracraft (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Craw (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Croft (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Craw/Croizat (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Cronin (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence "D" and Darden-Dupre, 1968-2002
    - "D" Correspondence, 1968-1998 (Box 12, Folder 3-9)
    - "D" Correspondence, 1999-2002 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Darden (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Dawkins (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Desmond (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Donoghue (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Douglas, Mary (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
    - Dounes (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Dupre (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence "E", "F", Eldredge-Ereshefsky, Farber-Funk, 1965-2001
    - "E" Correspondence, 1965-1999 (Box 14, Folder 2-6)
    - Eldredge (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Engles (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Eveshefsky (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
    - "F" Correspondence, 1968-1985 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
    - "F" Correspondence, 1986-2001 (Box 16, Folder 1-6)
    - Farber (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Farris (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Fine (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Ferguson (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Funk (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence "G" and Gayon-Ginnell, 1967-2002
    - "G" Correspondence, 1967-1992 (Box 17, Folder 4-8)
    - "G" Correspondence, 1993-2001 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
    - Gayon (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Geesink (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Ghiselin (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Ghiselin (2) (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Giere (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Glenn (Box 19, Folder 3-4)
    - Godfrey-Smith (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Godfrey-Smith (2) (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Gould, Steve (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Grantham (Box 20, Folder 3-4)
    - Greene, John (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Gregg (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Grehan (Box 20, Folder 7-8)
    - Grene (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Griesmer (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Griffiths (Box 21, Folder 4-5)
    - Griffiths (2) (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Grinnell (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence "H" and Heise-Horrath, 1967-2003
    - "H" Correspondence, 1967-1985 (Box 22, Folder 3-7)
    - "H" Correspondence, 1986-1998 (Box 23, Folder 1-7)
    - "H" Correspondence, 1999-2003 (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
    - Heise (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Heyes (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
    - Hill (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Hodge (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Hodgson (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Hurrath (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence "J" and "K", Johnson-Joravsky, Karabin-Kuhn, 1965-1999
    - "J" Correspondence, 1976-1999 (Box 26, Folder 1-2)
    - Johnson/Johnston (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Jones (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Joravsky (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - "K" Correspondence, 1965-1985 (Box 26, Folder 6-9)
    - "K" Correspondence, 1986-1999 (Box 27, Folder 1-5)
    - Karabin (Jail) (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Kory (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Kirkish (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Kircsh (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Kitcher (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Kitts (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Kludge (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Koertge (Box 28, Folder 4-5)
    - Kornet (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Kuhn (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence "L" and "M", Laland-Loyd and Maienshein-Murmann, 1960-2000
    - "L" Correspondence, 1965-1992 (Box 28, Folder 3-8)
    - "L" Correspondence, 1993-2000 (Box 30, Folder 1-4)
    - Laland (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Langman (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Langman (2) (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Latour (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Laudan (Box 31, Folder 3-4)
    - Little (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Little (2) (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Lloyd (Box 32, Folder 2-3)
    - "M" Correspondence, 1960-1975 (Box 32, Folder 4-5)
    - "M" Correspondence, 1976-1986 (Box 33, Folder 1-5)
    - "M" Correspondence, 1987-1994 (Box 34, Folder 1-4)
    - "M" Correspondence, 1995-2000 (Box 35, Folder 1-5)
    - Maienschein (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Marshall (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Mayr (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Mayr (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Maynard Smith (Box 36, Folder 3-4)
    - McMullin (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Mendelsohn (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Morrison (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Murmann (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence "N", "O", "P", and Nelson, O'Grady-Overmann, Platnick-Plotkin
    - "N" Correspondence, 1966-1999 (Box 37, Folder 1-4)
    - Nelson, G (Box 37, Folder 5-7)
    - "O" Correspondence, 1969-2004 (Box 38, Folder 1-3)
    - O'Grady (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Olby (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Oldroyd (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - Overmann (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - "P" Correspondence, 1966-1984 (Box 38, Folder 8-9)
    - "P" Correspondence, 1985-2004 (Box 39, Folder 1-3)
    - Platnick (Box 39, Folder 4-5)
    - Plotkin (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence "R" and Rauch-Ruse, 1964-2003
    - "R" Correspondence, 1964-1982 (Box 40, Folder 2-4)
    - "R" Correspondence, 1983-1995 (Box 41, Folder 1-6)
    - "R" Correspondence, 1997-2003 (Box 42, Folder 1-4)
    - Rauch (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Richards (Box 43, Folder 1-2)
    - Rieppel (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Rosenberg (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Rosenberg (2) (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Roll-Hansen (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Rosen (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - Ruse-1968-1988 (Box 44, Folder 4-6)
    - Ruse-1990-2000 (Box 45, Folder 1-5)
    - Ruse-2001-2003 (Box 46, Folder 1-2)
    - Ruse-2002-2003 (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence "S" and Salmon-Suppe, 1963-2003
    - "S" Correspondence, 1967-1977 (Box 46, Folder 3-6)
    - "S" Correspondence, 1978-1989 (Box 47, Folder 1-7)
    - "S" Correspondence, 1990-1997 (Box 48, Folder 1-7)
    - "S" Correspondence, 1998-2003 (Box 49, Folder 1-7)
    - Salmon, Wes (Box 49, Folder 8)
    - Salthe (Box 49, Folder 9)
    - Sarkar (Box 50, Folder 1)
    - Schaffner (Box 50, Folder 2-4)
    - Schmaus (Box 50, Folder 5)
    - Schnell (Box 50, Folder 6)
    - Speel (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Squires (Box 51, Folder 2)
    - Stevelay (Box 51, Folder 3-5)
    - Stinchcombe (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Sulloway (Box 51, Folder 7)
    - Singleton (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Sloan (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Smith (Box 52, Folder 3)
    - Sneath (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Sober (Box 52, Folder 5-6)
    - Sokal (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Scriven/Simpson (Box 52, Folder 8)
    - Seeskin (Box 52, Folder 9)
    - Suppe (Box 53, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence "T"-"V", Van der Steen- Vincente, 1965-2004
    - "T" Correspondence, 1965-1995 (Box 53, Folder 2-6)
    - "T" Correspondence, 1995-2004 (Box 54, Folder 1-4)
    - Vander Steen (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Van Regenmortal (Box 54, Folder 6)
    - Van Valen (Box 55, Folder 1)
    - Van Wyhe (Box 55, Folder 2)
    - Vasilyeva (Box 55, Folder 3)
    - Vicente (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence "W", Waters- Wilkins, 1968-2004
    - "W" Correspondence, 1967-1979 (Box 55, Folder 5)
    - "W" Correspondence, 1980-1999 (Box 56, Folder 1-6)
    - "W" Correspondence, 2000-2004 (Box 57, Folder 1-2)
    - Waters (Box 57, Folder 3)
    - Walsh (Box 57, Folder 4)
    - Wiley (Box 57, Folder 5-7)
    - Williams, Mary (Box 58, Folder 1-2)
    - Wilson, Jack (Box 58, Folder 3)
    - Wilson, Rob (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - Wilson, PS+EO (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - Wimsatt (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - Winsor (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - Wray (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - Wilkins (Box 59, Folder 4-5)
  - Correspondence "X"-"Z", NYRB Reviews and Correspondences-Barcelona Overheads
    - "X-Y-Z" Correspondence, 1996-1999 (Box 59, Folder 6)
    - "Y" Correspondence, 1973-2003 (Box 59, Folder 7)
    - "Z" Correspondence, 1969-2004 (Box 60, Folder 1)
- Manuscripts and Working Papers, II.
  This series contains working documents from educational projects that Hull created and materials for articles written for non-professional journals. There are materials for some of his books such as Science as a Process. There are also overheads for talks that Hull gave and, in addition, conference data to be found here. Further, there are materials relating to book reviews written for the New York Review of Books.
  - NYRB Review + Corr. (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - Bellagio Conference (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Data for Sciences as a Process (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Barcelona - Overheads (Box 60, Folder 5)
- Photograph Scrapbooks and Other Photographs, 1916-2008; III.
  This series is composed exclusively of photgraphic scrapbooks created by David Hull. They contain photographs of friends, relatives, and colleagues in a variety of settings. They document Hull's early life, his college education, his travels, his attendence at conferences and other topics. They were arranged chronologically by David Hull and have been left in that order.
  The contents of this series have been sequestered till 2044.
  - Photograph Scrapbooks and Other Photographs